do you remember when on your third time
ever playing tennis i put you on the
wall
do it again
good it was like crazy right
it was maybe a little bit too fast
you weren't quite ready for the wall but
yet you mastered it because you're so
gifted for tennis you're able to rally
on the first time on the wall
then remember i got a little bit um
let's say overconfident and i try to
teach you the slice remember that day
when i teach you the slice backhand
slice remember that i think you do i
remember that really and we were even
recording i was trying to teach you the
back and slides she didn't post the
video that's why it was a disaster
remember
it went very wrong it was very bad
teaching and so this would have gotten
negative views
i didn't post it because it didn't work
my instructions didn't work i realized
then that it was too early for slice
but you know i'm very
competitive with myself i want to teach
to the best possible ability that i have
so i would like you to try to teach you
the slice today again
also this slice is something that
will land on the territory of your enemy
what do you mean it doesn't go elsewhere
so
it what it the purpose of the size is
unpredictability of the ball you're
talking about sidespin
no like when they do this yeah i'll show
you stand around the baseline i'll show
you different types of slices what's the
purpose of this slice
the purpose of the slice anna
is to take the pace out of the ball and
give your opponent nothing to work with
exactly that's what i said oh that's
what he said
well i think what what this is what you
mean is side spin that's different from
slice yes it's a form of slice which is
called side spin we're not going to
learn that
that we're not going to get crazy today
okay it's crazy enough we're attempting
to to learn a slice so early on a side
spin will leave for later but sidespin
is this watch this side spin
see the ball
see how the ball jumps to the side i
hate those
okay
so at the recreational level these are
all accidental nobody's intending to do
that they're accidentally happening
and uh at the high level you'll see
sometimes where players will
intentionally do this but what you have
to learn which is a good shot
to have is a under spin backhand which
is a one-handed backhand that's why it's
going to be so tricky today because you
have a two-handed backhand so this one i
want to teach you to with one hand even
though you could hit with two hands too
and we'll test that out but it's a
one-handed backhand slice and the
advantage is watch watch this anna
you see how low that ball is yeah you
see the second bounce
now your opponent will have to bend
super low
and
the chances of them missing increase
dramatically because of that especially
at the recreational level because most
players will go hit a little bit too
hard when the ball is so low they'll
have to hit way up on the ball and they
very often hit long because of it
yeah
george george it's his breath and butter
the first slice
yeah the slice the first one was slice
the side spin
okay he does it all the time it's so
hard to it drives you crazy so we say
if we survive george then we're good
let's just well you know what you know
what's great about today's lesson yeah
not only i'm going to teach you how to
play the slice
but i'm also going to teach you how to
defend the slice
both ways
okay so i'm going to slice the tons of
balls to you and you're going to learn
how to play those balls
all right so let's get started with the
backhand slice
you can do a forehand slice too but
we're not going to do that because you
know you don't really need a four hand
slice but the back end slice because you
have two hands you have a little bit
less reach it sometimes comes in handy
to have a slice
if you're on a defense or if you get a
super low ball
again you have less range of motion with
two hands the racquet is a little bit
shorter you have less reach so it's more
convenient for extremely low balls to
slice them so it's a good shot to have
in your repertoire but let's go we're
going to start really slowly let's go up
to the net right there go up to the net
high to low is the key because when you
go high to low
that imparts under spin
high to low so if i go look if i go high
to low watch what happens to the ball
see how it spins this way
you see that yes that's under spin so if
i hit the ball like this if i go high to
low i'll get under spin
okay it's really cool
all right anna do you remember our viral
video yes
that was crazy video right you did so
well right off the bat
it was an it was like a magic magical
training session so good that people
thought we were lying yeah they said you
were advanced player
remember what we did in that lesson we
started from the contact
don't take the racket see as soon as you
start going back you lose control so i
want you to just get a good feeling for
the ball so you're going to start as
close to the contact as possible so this
is the contact here i want you to start
very close to the contact when you start
going back all the way here
keep holding the racket you're going to
get disconnected from the ball it's
going to be very
difficult to control it so you start
here and just think about what's going
to happen from the contact to the finish
okay
there it is and see how you're making
pretty much all the shots right now
beautiful job yes remember that we
started from the contact and just
finished we're going to do the exactly
the same thing on the slice yes the
mistake i did when i was teaching the
slice the last time
we started a little bit too high and
made too much of a backswing which made
the contact very impossible right right
so now we're going to get rid of this
area here we're going to start here very
close to the contact you want to slice
from here watch here and we're going to
slice from here okay and i guarantee
you're going to start making contact
okay
all right
[Laughter]
i guarantee it
i know you're still taking it back don't
take it back start here start here and
just cut it from there here we go
there you go anna
come on
this is crazy slices you're doing right
now
you see this
here we go
there it is
anna you see what i'm doing yeah i'm
shortening the backswing i'm making you
more aware of the contact now here's
ana listen
one pitfall of this shot
is what a lot of these guys that you
play against do is they use the wrist
yeah and now you get all kinds of
accidental stuff happening right so
don't come in like this here keep the
wrist stable watch it keep the wrist
stable here like show me the strings as
you're finishing show the strings to the
other side
here we go no back swing
anna you're doing the wrist a little bit
in the front
still a little bit of rest
okay what i want you to do is this as
you're finishing
have the tip of the racket towards there
not forward this way see tip of the
racket needs to be
towards the outside as you're finishing
like this yes all right
no back swing we're going to shorten the
back part of the stroke and
therefore allow you to really feel the
contact a lot better
don't take the racket back you see what
happens immediately you frame it
i know that was a very bad move right
there okay
yeah here we go
short to the contact and hit it
no good
what do you think terrible well it was
all framed right yeah it was all like
wrist and like elbow and all that watch
again
hold it
start very close to the ball
and go like that you see that see how
clean that is
that's all you got to do okay
it's a smaller motion than i think well
right now we're going to make it extra
small
don't play with the wrist come on
all right anna here watch this
here i'm going to stand behind you elbow
me elbow me on the back
elbow me
hit me with the elbow come on hit me
yeah
come on hit it a little harder ow
okay not with the racket go again hit me
with the elbow
there you go that's what with the elbow
this is your elbow well i'm afraid come
on just hit it there you go hit me with
the elbow
all right now when you hit your slice
i want you to think about getting the
elbow across
no take back
all right but why is it still so flimsy
and risky
you're going like
don't do that no wrist movement just
elbow
you know who roger federer is
yeah you heard about him right
they ask him once to give a tip on the
slice
and he said it's all about the elbow
that's what roger said and i was first
confused by that because it's really
not about the elbow because if you like
extend the elbow into the slice you
shorten the range of motion after the
contact and it ends up looking like like
this it looks really stiff but i know
what he meant he's accelerating with the
elbow across the body so when you
are imagining the stroke like what it
feels like to hit it it does feel like
you're using the elbow
so while you're not necessarily like
extending or or bending after the
contact you're not actively doing any
type of this movements here with the
elbow you are leading the way with the
elbow so i want you to think about that
you know what the elbow is yes it's this
thing right here okay so you go like
this watch you lead with the elbow right
here
that's what federer said okay this guy
is the best here we go
all right now why so crazy hard do it
slowly
do two miles an hour
there you go two miles an hour
because remember like any other shot
when you accelerate fast you have less
control over what's happening to your
stroke
okay
here we
i'll do it go
slowly
better
i want the speed limit right now in your
slice is two miles an hour if you go
over two miles an hour you're in big
trouble here we go
good
and again
anna you're hitting slices
you understand what's happening now
this is absolutely insane good
very good
anna this is crazy right now
insane
anna i'm proud of you
this is this is absolutely crazy what
you're doing right now
now you understand that like
five minutes ago when we first started
you were like framing every single one
[Laughter]
yeah right and now you see how they're
going nicely all right now let's back it
up to the service line
and naturally when you as you start
backing up in the court
the take back will need to increase
so
yeah but that's going to happen
naturally you're still going i'm afraid
it's not going to be over the net it's
going to happen naturally so you still
start here close to the ball
here we go
don't play with the wrist come on put
the racket a little higher just a little
bit here
do it again
anna
it's okay you have a little bit of
forehand grip too
going to continental
there you go remember if you go the more
you go towards the forehand grip on the
slice the more the racket face opens up
naturally so the more chance you have to
hit it with the frame
so while it is possible to slice with a
eastern forehand grip it's going to be
number one a lot of underspin that's not
always good because it slows the ball
weight down too much it lets it sit up
too high and also you have the chance of
hitting the frame so continental grip on
the slice is the best
that was a little better leave with the
elbow
anna this is a beautiful slice yes
and are you looking at all where the
ball is going or no why not
follow the ball look where it's going i
mean you're gonna have an opponent on
the other side so don't like hitting and
keep staring that way
and make it a little bit more realistic
just looking at you
i understand i've seen you for ages you
haven't seen me for a while yes okay
yeah i've been gone i've been in germany
all right here we go
i know that's too risky i don't like it
you just kind of scooped it with the
wrist
i like it leave it with the elbow come
on
i know it's too risky
yeah
slow it down you're going too hard now
slow down
honest it's like you are getting a
little bit of slice because you're going
down but like you're too loose here
remember not here
here tip of the racket towards the
outside you got what i'm saying
look how high you were going though
don't go that high stay close to the
ball you'll feel the contact much better
that's excellent do me one more and then
we'll go all the way back
all right let's go all the way to the
baseline actually give me one doing what
it's supposed to do absolutely
give me one more come a little closer
too loose right here and it opened up in
the shoulder
okay but you can't open up a little bit
i don't mind that that's okay
that's fine i don't mind that it's okay
to do it's okay to go like this a little
bit but what you got to avoid is
snapping here with the wrist
all right
best slice of your life
unbelievable
do you see the difference how the ball
stayed low all right now we back up to
the baseline
to be able to
get over the net
excellent question now we're not gonna
be able to get away with this we don't
have enough swing momentum
not enough so now we're gonna have to go
back a little bit okay naturally uh what
happens with players it starts happening
on its own that's why i like doing these
progressions yes also you've been seeing
so so let's just let's just continue to
stay here and see if you do it by
yourself without forcing it okay
it's okay come again
the racket face is too open
so yeah so if you hit the slice
with an extremely open racket face
you'll hit the ball too thin
like this you see this
so you got to close that racket face
again continental grip helps
tremendously with that there we go
anna that's a slice
leave with the elbow
leave with the elbow it's okay what is
the elbow
what is the elbow this is forgot again
[Laughter]
so in other words don't allow this to
happen here
yeah this so it keeps it keeps this
protected in a way it keeps the here
look it's just like messing up with me
the distance is longer so i feel like i
have to
send it there with this opening
well maybe you're where
we uh went to the base now a little too
early it's quite possible that we have
this
that we have to stay on the service line
a little bit longer it's possible that
we're going to test these four but it's
very possible we're progressing a little
too fast but you see how it can mess up
with me right because we're increasing
the distance not just you not just to
everyone because with bigger distance
you have to swing a little faster any
time you swing faster you lose control
over what's happening around the contact
that's why when you're building strokes
hitting slowly at first is huge because
you can feel what's going on much more
and you have more control over it as
well
i'll do it again
all right you know what let's back up
let's let's take a step back and we'll
go we'll go between the service line and
the baseline we'll go three quarter
right here we'll try from here okay
oh my goodness
the best slice i've ever seen from you
that was sick right there it didn't go
through it was millimeter millimeter too
low here we go
tip of the racket to the outside and i
know you made that one but i didn't like
the technique here we go
use that left hand anna the left hand
will can support your racket
otherwise your arm is going to feel
super heavy you hold the rack about a
throat here
as you're preparing to start the stroke
anna was it good
did you see it yeah because you keep
looking that way
you saw that i saw the trajectory yeah
it's a slice
anna
that's it yeah all right now
you did a fantastic job today on this is
crazy what you did
you learned slice yeah no it's not match
ready by any means we have to practice
it a lot but
here's what i want to try i wanna try
one more thing we're not ready to go to
the baseline yet we realized that it's
too difficult right now yes
maybe even this is too far back i want
you to practice slices from the service
line
and i want you to get inside the service
line a little bit and do it off my feet
i'm going to feed it to you and you're
going to try to slice it okay without
dropping on the floor no it's going to
drop on the ground
good and i turn the sideways a little
more turn sideways
sideways yeah turn sideways
come a little closer
beautiful job anna that's the slice
a little high but it's okay i like it
a little too thin close that racket face
okay
it's spinning a lot that's underspin
on a wonderful slice
go a little bit more towards the middle
go again
not bad i want one that's kind of low
it's a little high there
anna wow
wow
are you kidding me
you don't know it was good
it was the best slice i've ever seen you
had
by far the best slice of your life cool
anna this is actually quite an amazing
thing that happened today i didn't think
it would be possible
but i was able to teach you the slice
you know what made the biggest
difference
controlling the contact being aware of
the contact not starting too far back
here because then as you accelerate you
kind of lose what's supposed to happen
here by being closer to the contact i
think you got the hang of what a slice
is all about yeah and i'm trying to go
high to low on the ball
biggest problem that you have is the
wrist is very active we can see this the
way you're finishing it's going to take
some practice we have to keep working on
that
and
but having said that there was an
amazing improvement in just a few
minutes you were able to get some nice
slices today all right great job
you